<person xml:id="AIND-D00104" source="298336649470">
    <persName type="full" xml:lang="ar">إبراهيم بن حسن برهان الدين المناوي ثم القاهري التاجر ابن عليبة</persName>
    <persName type="name_only" xml:lang="ar">إبراهيم بن حسن</persName>
    <persName type="nisbah" xml:lang="ar" ref="#TMP-N-00102">المناوي</persName>
    <persName type="nisbah" xml:lang="ar" ref="#TMP-N-00010">القاهري</persName>
    <persName type="laqab" xml:lang="ar">برهان الدين</persName>
    <persName type="shuhrah" xml:lang="ar">ابن عليبة</persName>
    <sex value="M"/>
    <birth>
        <placeName ref="#TMP-L-00035">مسه بن سلسل</placeName>
    </birth>
    <death when-custom="0875-07-03" when="1471-01-04" cert="high">
        <placeName ref="gn:104515">مكة</placeName>
        <note xml:lang="en">Died on the night of Thursday, 3rd Rajab 875 AH.</note>
    </death>
    <listRelation>
        <relation type="personal" subtype="teacher" n="1" active="#TMP-P-000278" passive="#AIND-D00104">
            <desc type="method" xml:lang="ar">اعتقادهم والوقوف مع إشارتهم</desc>
            <desc type="field" ref="#TMP-S-00023" xml:lang="ar">التصوف</desc>
        </relation>
        <relation type="personal" subtype="teacher" n="2" active="#TMP-P-000279" passive="#AIND-D00104">
            <desc type="method" ref="#TMP-S-00034" xml:lang="ar">صحب | الصحبة</desc>
            <desc type="field" ref="#TMP-S-00023" xml:lang="ar">التصوف</desc>
        </relation>
        <relation type="personal" subtype="son" active="#TMP-P-000280" passive="#AIND-D00104"><desc xml:lang="ar">البدري حسن</desc></relation>
        <relation type="personal" subtype="son" active="#TMP-P-000281" passive="#AIND-D00104"><desc xml:lang="ar">المحيوي عبد القادر</desc></relation>
        <relation type="personal" subtype="patron" active="#TMP-P-000282" passive="#AIND-D00104"><desc xml:lang="ar">الفوي</desc><note xml:lang="ja">ムナーウィーの家を訪れる聖者の一人</note></relation>
        <relation type="personal" subtype="patron" active="#TMP-P-000283" passive="#AIND-D00104"><desc xml:lang="ar">الصندلي</desc><note xml:lang="ja">ムナーウィーの家を訪れる聖者の一人</note></relation>
        <relation type="personal" subtype="patron" active="#TMP-P-000284" passive="#AIND-D00104"><desc xml:lang="ar">إمام الكاملية</desc><note xml:lang="ja">ムナーウィーの家を訪れる聖者の一人</note></relation>
        <relation type="personal" subtype="patron" active="#TMP-P-000285" passive="#AIND-D00104"><desc xml:lang="ar">ابن الجمال</desc><note xml:lang="ja">ムナーウィーの家を訪れる聖者の一人</note></relation>
        <relation type="personal" subtype="patron" active="#TMP-P-000286" passive="#AIND-D00104"><desc xml:lang="ar">ابن شيخه الغمري</desc><note xml:lang="ja">ムナーウィーの家を訪れる聖者の一人</note></relation>
        <relation type="personal" subtype="friend" active="wd:Q4120128" passive="#AIND-D00104"><desc xml:lang="ar">السخاوي</desc><note xml:lang="ja">サハーウィーもムナーウィーとの座談(mujālasa)を楽しむ者たちの一人だったとされる。</note></relation>
    </listRelation>
    <event type="residence" n="1">
        <placeName ref="gn:360630">القاهرة</placeName>
    </event>
    <event type="hajj" n="2">
        <placeName ref="gn:104515">مكة</placeName>
        <note xml:lang="en">performed multiple times</note>
    </event>
    <event type="jāwara" n="3">
        <placeName ref="gn:104515">مكة</placeName>
        <note xml:lang="en">Resided after performing Hajj (mujāwara).</note>
    </event>
    <event type="burial" n="4" when-custom="0875-07-03" cert="high">
        <placeName ref="wd:Q42004">المعلاة</placeName>
        <note xml:lang="en">Buried on the same day as death.</note>
    </event>
    <state n="1" type="office" ref="wd:Q215536">
        <label xml:lang="ar">تاجر</label>
        <label xml:lang="ar-Latn">tājir</label>
    </state>
    <note type="translation" xml:lang="ja">イブラーヒーム・ブン・ハサン、ブルハーン・アッディーン。ミナーウィー出身で後にカーヒリーの人。商人であり、イブン・ウライバという通称で知られた。「ウライバ」は「ウルバ」の縮小形、最初の子音にダーマを付し、二番目の子音は静止、最後の二番目の子音にファトハを付し、最後にバーを付す。彼はマスハ・ブン・サルサルで生まれた。商売に従事し、その中で多くの幸運と祝福を得た。それは彼の誠実さ、貧者への愛情と彼らを信じる心、そして彼らの指示に従う態度によるもので、アフマド・アル＝ハッシャーブのように、彼らとの多くの出来事を語っていた。さらに、シャイフ・ムハンマド・アル＝ガムリーや他のスーフィーたちに師事した。カイロにある自身のモスクのために、灯油、毎日水を供給すること、読誦、毎月定められた夜に食事、3ヶ月ごとにブハーリーの読誦、その他、近くに建設したワクフから収入を得て多くの費用を賄った。そして彼の家は、アル＝ファウィー、アッ＝サンダリー、アル＝カーミリヤのマムルーク長、イブン・アル＝ジャマール、そして師であるアル＝ガムリーの弟子たちのような聖者たちの拠り所となり、さらには彼らの家族と共に滞在する場所ともなった。これら全てを、クルアーン読誦と内省の継続、そして必要最小限を除いて世俗の人々と交わることを望まない美しい資質をもって行った。また、二人の息子、バドリー・ハサンとムヒヤウィー・アブドゥルカーディルが過度に努力し、そのために疲弊しても何の利益も得られなかったことを彼は否定した。彼は複数回ハッジを行い、マッカに滞在した。私(サハーウィー)も彼の座談を楽しむ者の一人だった。彼は善行と礼拝において絶えず進歩し続け、875年ラジャブ月3日木曜日の夜にマッカで亡くなり、アル＝ムアッラーに埋葬された。彼のような人物は同世代にはいなかった。彼と私たちにアッラーの慈悲がありますように。</note>
    <note type="translation" xml:lang="en">Ibrāhīm ibn Ḥasan Burhān al-Dīn al-Mināwī, then al-Qāhirī, was a merchant known as Ibn ʿUlayba. His birth was in Masah ibn Salsal. He engaged in trade and was blessed with much fortune and prosperity due to his sincerity, love for the poor, belief in them, and adherence to their guidance, like Aḥmad al-Khashāb, to the extent that he narrated many incidents with them. Moreover, he companioned Shaykh Muḥammad al-Ghamrī and other Sufi practitioners. He covered many expenses for his mosque in Cairo, including fuel oil, daily water provision, recitation, food on the appointed night each month, for the recitation of Bukhārī in three months, and other matters, all supported by an endowment (rubʿ) he established nearby. His house became a resort for the pious, such as al-Fawī, al-Ṣandalī, the Imām of al-Kāmiliyya, Ibn al-Jamāl, and Ibn Shaykhuhu al-Ghamrī, and even a place for others to reside with their families. All this he did while constantly engaging in recitation and contemplation, possessing beautiful qualities, and having no desire to mix with worldly people except as needed. He also disapproved of his two sons, al-Badrī Ḥasan and al-Muḥyawī ʿAbd al-Qādir, for their excessive efforts, which caused them fatigue but yielded no substantial gain. He performed the Hajj multiple times and resided in Mecca. I (al-Sakhāwī) was among those who enjoyed his company. He continually progressed in good deeds and prayer until he died in Mecca on the night of Thursday, the third of Rajab in the year 875 AH, and was buried in al-Muʿallā. He left no one like him among his peers. May Allah have mercy on him and us.</note>
    <respStmt>
        <resp xml:lang="ja">初版作成</resp>
        <persName>Shinoda</persName>
        <date when="2026-05-11"/>
    </respStmt>
    <respStmt>
        <resp xml:lang="ja">修正・追記</resp>
        <persName>Kumakura</persName>
        <date when="2026-05-11"/>
</person>