<person xml:id="AIND-D00095" source="913175478502">
    <persName type="full" xml:lang="ar">إبراهيم بن حجي بن علي بن عيسى بن خضر بن إبراهيم بن قاسم الشريف المعمر أبو إسحاق الحسني الطرابلسي الأصل</persName>
    <persName type="name_only" xml:lang="ar">إبراهيم بن حجي بن علي</persName>
    <persName type="nisbah" xml:lang="ar" ref="#TMP-N-00079">الحسني</persName>
    <persName type="nisbah" xml:lang="ar" ref="gn:266826">الطرابلسي</persName>
    <persName type="honorific" xml:lang="ar">الشريف</persName>
    <persName type="shuhrah" xml:lang="ar">المعمر</persName>
    <persName type="kunyah" xml:lang="ar">أبو إسحاق</persName>
    <sex value="M"/>
    <birth when-custom="0740" when="1339" cert="low">
        <placeName ref="gn:266826">طرابلس</placeName>
        <note xml:lang="ja">本人は725年生まれを主張していたが、専門家たちはこれを批判。アル＝タキー・アル＝ファースィーは740年頃かそれより少し前と推定。</note>
    </birth>
    <death when-custom="0832-04" when="1429-01" cert="medium">
        <note xml:lang="ja">832年第一ラビーウ月初め(mustahall)没という説もある。</note>
    </death>
    <listRelation>
        <relation type="personal" subtype="teacher" n="1" active="#TMP-P-000275" passive="#AIND-D00095">
            <desc type="method" ref="#TMP-S-00003" xml:lang="ar">سمع | السماع</desc>
            <desc type="field" ref="#TMP-S-00002" xml:lang="ar">الحديث | علم الحديث</desc>
            <note xml:lang="ja">アル＝ハッジャールからの聴聞の主張は、ファースィーらによって否定されている。</note>
        </relation>
        <relation type="personal" subtype="teacher" n="2" active="#TMP-P-000275" passive="#AIND-D00095">
            <desc type="method" ref="#TMP-S-00004" xml:lang="ar">أجاز | إجازة</desc>
            <desc type="field" ref="#TMP-S-00002" xml:lang="ar">الحديث | علم الحديث</desc>
            <note xml:lang="ja">アル＝ハッジャールからのイジャーザ授与の主張は、ファースィーらによって否定されている。</note>
        </relation>
        <relation type="personal" subtype="teacher" n="3" active="#TMP-P-000173" passive="#AIND-D00095">
            <desc type="method" ref="#TMP-S-00003" xml:lang="ar">سمع | السماع</desc>
            <desc type="field" ref="#TMP-S-00002" xml:lang="ar">الحديث | علم الحديث</desc>
            <bibl xml:lang="ar">عدة أجزاء</bibl>
            <bibl xml:lang="ar-Latn">ʿiddat ajzāʾ</bibl>
            <note xml:lang="ja">アル＝サドル・アル＝マイドゥーミーからの聴聞。可能性はあるが根拠は確認されていない。</note>
        </relation>
        <relation type="personal" subtype="other" active="#TMP-P-000274" passive="#AIND-D00095">
            <desc type="relationship_type" xml:lang="ar">ربيب</desc>
            <desc xml:lang="ja">スライマーン・ブン・ジブリールはイブラーヒームの継父(母の夫)。そのため「イブラーヒーム・ブン・スライマーン・ブン・マルワーン」とも呼ばれた。</desc>
        </relation>
    </listRelation>
    <event type="residence" n="1">
        <placeName ref="gn:285066">الخليل</placeName>
    </event>
    <note type="personalia" xml:lang="ja">生年について誇張していたとの評価がある。ハッジャールおよびマイドゥーミーから学んだとされているが、いずれも根拠はない。スライマーン・ブン・ジブリールの継子であることから、イブラーヒーム・ブン・スライマーン・ブン・マルワーンとも呼ばれる。</note>
    <note type="translation" xml:lang="ja">イブラーヒーム・ブン・ハッジー・ブン・アリー・ブン・イーサー・ブン・ヒドル・ブン・イブラーヒーム・ブン・カーシム、シャリーフ・アル＝ムアンマル、アブー・イスハーク・アル＝ハサニー・アル＝タラーブルシーは、元々トリポリ出身で、ヘブロンに住み、スライマーン・ブン・ジブリールの継子であった。彼の誕生はヒジュラ暦725年とされているが、アル＝タキー・アル＝ファースィーはそれを批判し、彼が誇張していると述べた。ファースィーは彼を試した結果、彼が限度を超えており、彼の誕生は740年頃かそれより少し前である可能性が高いことを知った。イブン・ナーシル・アル＝ディーンも同様に、彼がアル＝ハッジャールから聴聞したと述べたが、それは正しくないと述べている。また、他の者も、彼がアル＝サドル・アル＝マイドゥーミーから数冊の書を聴聞したと述べたが、そのことは一部の学生が彼の言葉で「我らのシャイフがその辞書(『ムアジャム』)の第二部で言った」と朗誦した際に示唆されたものの、マイドゥーミーからの聴聞が真実である証拠は現れなかった。その後、彼はアル＝ハッジャールが彼にイジャーザを与えたと主張し、自身が(ヒジュラ暦)725年に生まれたと主張し、請願書に書き記し、彼の事情を深く調査しなかった何人かの者から(書を)朗誦された後、彼の状況が明らかになった。ハーフィズ・アル＝タキー・アル＝ファースィーやこの分野の他の人々は、私(サハーウィー)に彼の誇張とアル＝ハッジャールからのイジャーザの主張の誤りを語った。マイドゥーミーからの聴聞は可能であったかもしれないが、その根拠は明らかにならなかった。彼は(ヒジュラ暦)832年のラビーウ・アル＝アーヒル月に死去した。もし彼が正直であったなら、アル＝ハッジャールが100歳を超えたように彼もそうであっただろうし、彼の学習と伝達の時期の間にはさらに多くの時間が経っていたはずである。なぜならアル＝ハッジャールが最も古く聴聞したものは736年であり、730年に亡くなっているからである。これは、もしアル＝ハッジャールが彼にイジャーザを与えたとすれば、それは730年かそれ以前であり、彼は730年以降に遅れて現れたことになる。「正しくは、アル＝ハッジャールから特別な、確認されたイジャーザによって最後にハディースを伝えたのは、我らのシャイフ、アル＝ザイン・アブー・フサインである。」と(我らの)シャイフは述べ、その辞書(『ムアジャム』)の第一部でも簡潔に彼を批判している。しかし、シャイフは、彼が722年に生まれたと主張し、729年に私たちにイジャーザを与えたと述べた。私(サハーウィー)は言う。他の者は彼の死をラビーウ・アル＝アウワル月初めと記録している。彼が自分の辞書の二つの部分で彼に言及しているにもかかわらず、その情報から彼を省略している。私には、マイドゥーミーに関する伝記層に書かれていることが、彼の母親の夫への帰属であると伝わった。それで、彼はイブラーヒーム・ブン・スライマーン・ブン・マルワーンと言われた。イブン・ナーシル・アル＝ディーンは、彼がアル＝ハッジャールから特別なイジャーザを与えられた一人であると認めた。「そして、彼に言及することで、私たちは『アル＝インティサール・リ＝サマー・アル＝ハッジャール・ワ＝アル＝マイル・ラハ』と題する私たちの著作を終えた。」と(我らの)シャイフや他の多くの人々は述べた。</note>
    <note type="translation" xml:lang="en">Ibrāhīm b. Ḥajjī b. ʿAlī b. ʿĪsā b. Khiḍr b. Ibrāhīm b. Qāsim, al-Sharīf al-Muʿammar Abū Isḥāq al-Ḥasanī, originally from Tripoli, a resident of Hebron, and the stepson of Sulaymān b. Jibrīl. It was mentioned that he was born in the year 725 AH, but al-Taqī al-Fāsī disputed this, saying that he exaggerated and that when al-Fāsī tested him on the matter, he realized that Ibrāhīm had exceeded the limit, and that his birth could be around 740 AH or a little before. Similarly, Ibn Nāṣir al-Dīn stated that Ibrāhīm claimed to have heard from al-Ḥajjār, but this was not verified. Others likewise mentioned that he claimed to have heard several parts (of hadith) from al-Ṣadr al-Mīdūmī, and some students read to him, quoting our shaykh in the second part of his dictionary (muʿjam), but the authenticity of his hearing from al-Mīdūmī was not apparent. Then he claimed that al-Ḥajjār granted him an ijāza, and that he was born in the year 725 AH. He wrote on petitions, and some who did not thoroughly investigate his case read to him, after which his true situation became clear. Al-Ḥāfiẓ al-Taqī al-Fāsī and others in this field informed me of his exaggeration and the invalidity of his claim to an ijāza from al-Ḥajjār. As for his hearing from al-Mīdūmī, it is possible, but no basis for it has appeared. He died in Rabīʿ al-Ākhir in the year 832 AH. If he had been truthful, he would have resembled al-Ḥajjār in exceeding a hundred years, and even more so in the time between his reception of knowledge and his transmission of it, for al-Ḥajjār's earliest recorded hearing was in 736 AH, and he died in 730 AH. If al-Ḥajjār granted him ijāza, this would have been in 730 AH or before, but he appeared after 730 AH. Our shaykh said, "The truth is that the last person to transmit from al-Ḥajjār with a specific, verified ijāza was our shaykh, al-Zayn Abū Ḥusayn." Our shaykh also alluded to criticizing him briefly in the first part of his dictionary, saying that he (Ibrāhīm) claimed to have been born in 722 AH and granted us ijāza in 729 AH. I (al-Sakhāwī) say: Others dated his death to the beginning of Rabīʿ al-Awwal. Despite mentioning him in both parts of his dictionary, he omitted him from his biographical notices. It reached me that what was written in the biographical section concerning al-Mīdūmī attributed him to his mother's husband, so he was called Ibrāhīm b. Sulaymān b. Marwān. Ibn Nāṣir al-Dīn endorsed his being among those to whom al-Ḥajjār granted a specific ijāza. Our shaykh and many others said: "And with his mention, we concluded our work titled 『al-Intiṣār li-Samāʿ al-Ḥajjār wa-l-Mayl Lahā』."</note>
    <respStmt>
        <resp xml:lang="ja">初版作成</resp>
        <persName>Shinoda</persName>
        <date when="2026-05-11"/>
    </respStmt>
    <respStmt>
        <resp xml:lang="ja">修正・追記</resp>
        <persName>Kumakura</persName>
        <date when="2026-05-11"/>
    </respStmt>
</person>